what if I asked you to design a box sure
you could make something but it's hard
to make anything meaningful or useful
because you don't know what the box
needs to do
there aren't enough constraints but if I
was a little bit more specific and told
you that it was a pizza box
suddenly the task is a bit easier you
know the shape of pizza um it's round
and you know enough about it to start to
develop more nuanced concepts if I told
you that this pizza box needs to fit a
16 inch diameter pizza and the box must
be made from compostable molded fiber
and it's even more clear if this box
needs to have several other pizzas
stacked on top of it I know to add in
some structural ribbing to make the box
stronger so this is important because
this shows you that the more specific
you are with constraints the easier it
is to design the shape that your designs
take are dictated by what the designs
need to do or how they should function
this is the crux of the phrase form
follows function this is a quote that
was originally coined by architect Louis
Sullivan in the late 1800s and it still
holds true today and it will probably
always hold true the first thing that I
do when I start a project was
established a design criteria it forces
you to be very specific about what a
success will look like for a problem
you're solving and it takes a lot of
subjectivity out of the design process
you can't just arbitrarily choose red
for the products color just because you
like it every design decision should be
made in service of a specific goal and
this is really really important when
you're sort of designing for form
following the function when you present
a design without a clear goal to
engineers marketer senior designers or
business people this is what you sound
like
now you can't really make a design
criteria unless you understand the
problem very intimately and this sort of
problem scoping is done through design
research so I won't get into the details
of design research right now for this
video in the meantime a really good book
on design research is called designing
for growth I
recommended another thing that you can
think about with form following function
is to have visual indicators so properly
using contrasting colors materials and
shapes is a really good way to highlight
function for example the equal sign on
this Brown calculator is a great example
of that
same thing with this messenger bag these
color changes highlight the most
important or most used touch points on
the object the color change draws your
eye in and this is especially useful
when you're working in high stress
environments so in an airplane cockpit
mistakes can mean life or death that's
why many of the buttons in the cockpit
are distinctly different shapes and
colors you don't want to mistake one
button for another now I've never flown
a plane but I'm willing to bet that the
buttons with the red covers on them are
probably only meant for an emergency
this is the power of visual indicators
and form following function it tells you
how to use the object just by looking at
it the form following function really
the best thing that you can do is make
it so that the user can't do something
the wrong way so remember all the USB
inputs
well the visual indicator for which
orientation to insert it is never easy
enough to identify at least in my
opinion in many other people's opinions
and they also require just a little bit
too much force to insert so sometimes
you end up flipping it back and forth
like two or three times before you get
it right now thankfully USBC can be
inserted in both directions or
orientations so this is a problem of the
past and USBC is a great example of form
following function by making a design
foolproof another thing to think about
with functionality is mapping a great
example of very confusing mapping are
with stovetops so I always have trouble
figuring out which knob controls which
burner and a more practical control
array would be one that's aligned with
the stovetop burners now I can almost
guarantee you that there are mechanical
constraints here but from a usability
perspective this makes way more sense
and this particular example is mentioned
by Don Norman in the design of everyday
things which is another
I highly recommend one of the biggest
determining factors in the function look
and feel of your design is the
manufacturing method so a chair that's
injection molded versus one that's made
from bent plywood all yield completely
different visual and functional results
sometimes simply switching up the
manufacturing method is enough to make
the functionality and aesthetic of the
design completely novel and new each
manufacturing method has different
strengths and weaknesses and this is
usually the determining factor in
whether a feature or design detail can
be implemented the last thing I want to
talk about is form following convention
so for example every production may
drill i've ever seen has a trigger in
the same place except for one which was
designed by Porsche so this design has
the trigger on top of the device now
it's totally possible this is a superior
design but power drills have been around
for over a hundred years and they've
always had the trigger in the same spot
so changing that trigger location goes
against a hundred years of convention
and for this reason radically new ideas
are often not accepted customers are
just used to the status quo and even if
the new idea is much better people will
be slow to adopt those new ideas in
addition to that you may be going
against legal regulations that are
heavily entrenched so I want to make it
clear that I'm not saying that you
should blindly follow convention that I
would never suggest that all I'm saying
is that you need to be aware of those
conventions and figure out how to
navigate any potential pushback from
customers what I'm basically talking
about here is ringing a noise mantra of
the most advanced yet acceptable I'm
thinking about making a video about this
at some point so I hope this video was
helpful subscribe if you want to see
more content like this it really
motivates me to continue on with the
channel and leave a like if you enjoyed
the video I'll link the books that I
mentioned in the description and thank
you so much for checking this out guys
and I hope you learned something
you